so how can we calculate the speed of a
satellite that is moving in a circular
orbit at a height of thirty eight
hundred kilometers above the surface of
the earth so let's draw a picture so
we're gonna say this is the earth and
here is a satellite that orbits the
earth maybe I could draw a better
picture
what can we do to find the speed of that
satellite well first we need to derive
an equation this satellite has a
centripetal force any object that moves
with circular motion has a centripetal
force and it turns out that gravity
provides the centripetal force in this
example this force is the gravitational
force that keeps it moving in a circle
so we're gonna set the force of gravity
equal to the centripetal force and let's
say that the satellite has a mass
lowercase M and the earth has a mass
Capital m so to calculate the
gravitational force between two objects
its G times the mass of the Earth times
the mass of the satellite divided by the
squared distance between the Centers of
the earth and the satellite the
centripetal force acting on the
satellite because the satellite is
moving in a circle it's gonna be the
mass times the square of the speed
divided by the radius so what we can do
is cancel em and if we multiply both
sides by R we can cancel an R so we're
left with GM over R is equal to V
squared so now we need to take the
square root of both sides so the speed
of a satellite is the square root of the
universal gravitation constant times the
mass of the Earth divided by the
distance between the Centers
now let's think about what we already
know we know the gravitational constant
is a fixed number we have the mass of
the earth now what is our in its problem
what should we replace art with R is not
the radius of the earth and it's not the
height above the surface of the earth
it's actually the sum of those two
values so let me draw a better picture
to illustrate it so let's say this is
the earth and this is the satellite so
first we have the radius of the earth
which is six point three eight times 10
to the 6 meters and we have the height
of the satellite above the surface of
the earth which is thirty-eight hundred
kilometers to add these two we need to
make sure that the unit matches so one
kilometer is a thousand meters so 3800
kilometers that's 3.8 million meters you
got to multiply this by a thousand so
that's equivalent to three point eight
times 10 to the 6 meters so R is the sum
of these two numbers
so if we add six point three eight times
ten to the six plus three point eight
times ten to the six that's equal to one
point zero one eight times ten to the
seven meters so R is the distance
between the Sun of the earth and the
center of the satellite now we can use
the formula so we have G the
gravitational constant six point six
seven times ten to the minus eleven
multiplied by the mass of the earth
which is five point nine seven times ten
to the 24 divided by R which is one
point zero one eight times ten to the
seven meters
so the speed of the satellite let me
erase a few things
the speed of the satellite is six
thousand two hundred fifty four point
three meters per second so that's how
fast it's going now that we have this
speed what is the period of the
satellite in hours so what do you think
we need to do in order to calculate the
period so let's say this is the earth
and this is the satellite the satellite
travels around the earth and it's moving
at constant speed whenever you have an
object moving at constant speed you can
use this equation D is equal to V T so V
is d over T the distance around a circle
is the circumference which is 2 pi R and
the time it takes to complete one
revolution or one cycle around the
circle is the period now we need to
solve for T so I'm going to multiply
both sides by T so VT is equal to 2 PI R
and dividing both sides by V the period
is 2 PI R over V and we have the R value
the R value is this number so the period
is going to be the circumference 2 pi
times 1 point 0 1 8 times 10 to the 7
divided by the speed of the satellite
which is 62 54.3 meters per second
so you should get 10,000 and 227 seconds
now let's convert that into hours
so the 60 seconds in a minute and
there's 60 minutes in one hour so we
could cancel the unit seconds and
minutes so it's ten thousand two hundred
twenty seven divided by sixty and
divided by sixty again so the period is
about two point eight four hours so
that's how long it's going to take for
this satellite to orbit the Earth at
this speed and at this orbital radius
now let's move on to our second question
a geosynchronous satellite is one that
stays above the same point on the
equator of the earth what is the period
of such a satellite in seconds so let's
say if this satellite stays at the same
point so it's gonna rotate at the same
rate as the Earth rotates it's gonna
have the same angular speed now it takes
the earth 24 hours to rotate on its
internal axis so the satellite is gonna
take 24 hours for the satellite to
revolve around the earth make sure you
understand the difference between
rotation and revolution when an object
rotates it rotates about its internal
axis so like the earth it has its own
internal access that it rotates around
now the satellite revolves around an
external axis which is basically the
axis of the earth but that's outside of
the satellite so it's external so the
satellite traveling around the earth its
revolving the earth spinning on its own
axis it's rotating
so what is the period of that satellite
so as we mentioned it takes 24 hours for
the earth to rotate on its own axis so
for geosynchronous satellite it's going
to be 24 hours for it to revolve around
the earth now we need to convert that
into seconds so one hour is equal to 60
minutes and one minute is equivalent to
60 seconds so it's 24 times 60 times
another 60 so it's 86,400 seconds so
that's the period now let's move on to
Part B what is the satellites height
above the surface of the earth in
kilometers so how can we use the period
to calculate the height of the satellite
so let's draw a picture so let's say
this is the earth and this is the
satellite so let's say that lowercase R
is the radius of the earth and H is the
height of the satellite capital R is the
distance between the centre of the earth
and the set of the satellite our goal is
to calculate H the height above the
surface of the earth so let's write this
r is equal to h plus lowercase R
now somehow we need an equation that
relates the period with R so let's see
if we can come up with such an equation
now recall that we said the speed of the
satellite it's a square root of GM over
R and we're gonna use that equation for
Part C but we don't know what R is
so we got to find that first now V
squared it's gonna be GM over R and
without the square root and we call on
the last problem that V is 2 PI R over T
so I'm gonna replace V with 2 PI over T
so I'm gonna have 2 PI R over the period
and that's squared and that's equal to
GM over R so 2 squared is 4 so we're
gonna have 4 PI squared R squared over T
squared is equal to GM over R and now
I'm running out of space so let's get
rid of some stuff
so what I'm gonna do now is I'm gonna
cross multiply so I'm gonna have 4pi
squared times R cubed that's R squared
times R and on the right side GM times T
squared so I can leave the equation like
this or I could solve for R so I'm gonna
do that
so RQ who's going to be GM T squared
over 4pi squared and then taking the
cube root of both sides
r is going to be the cube root of GM t
squared over 4pi squared so this
equation allows me to calculate the
radius of the orbit if i know the period
so this is gonna be the cube root of g
which is six point six seven times ten
to the minus eleven times the mass of
the earth which you can find a base on
the last problem that's five point nine
seven times ten to the twenty four and
then multiplied by the period which is
86,400 and don't forget to square it and
all of this will be divided by four five
squared
you may want to put this in parentheses
taking the cube root is the same as
raising it to the 1/3 power so you
should have an R value of 4.2 2 times 10
to the 7 meters but we're not quite
finished yet
we need to find the height so the height
is going to be the radius of the orbit
minus the radius of the earth so that's
going to be four point two two times ten
to the seven and then minus the radius
of the earth which is in the last
problem
six point three eight times ten to the
six meters so this is equal to three
point five eight times ten to the seven
meters now let's convert that to
kilometers so there's a thousand meters
per kilometer so we got to divide that
by a thousand and so it's thirty-five
thousand eight hundred kilometers so
that's how high this satellite is above
the surface of the earth now the last
thing that we need to do is we need to
calculate the speed of the satellite
so let's go back to this equation
so we have G we have the mass of the
earth five point nine seven times ten to
the twenty four and the orbital radius
is four point 22 times 10 to the seven
that's the distance between the center
of the earth and the center of the
satellite
so the speed of the satellite is 3072
meters per second and so that's it for
this video so now you know how to
calculate the speed of the satellite the
satellites height above the surface of
the earth and also the period of the
satellite if you need to thanks for
watching